Copyright © 2018 by Summersdale Publishers Ltd.



First Racehorse Publishing Edition 2020.



All rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced in any manner without the express written consent of the publisher, except in the case of brief excerpts in critical reviews or articles. All inquiries should be addressed to Racehorse Publishing, 307 West 36th Street, 11th Floor, New York, NY 10018.



Racehorse Publishing books may be purchased in bulk at special discounts for sales promotion, corporate gifts, fund-raising, or educational purposes. Special editions can also be created to specifications. For details, contact the Special Sales Department, Skyhorse Publishing, 307 West 36th Street, 11th Floor, New York, NY 10018 or info@skyhorsepublishing.com.



Racehorse Publishing™ is a pending trademark of Skyhorse Publishing, Inc.®, a Delaware corporation.



Visit our website at www.skyhorsepublishing.com.



10 9 8 7 6 5 4 3 2 1



Cover artwork by Shutterstock.com



Interior artwork credited in the back matter



Print ISBN: 978-1-63158-492-3



E-Book ISBN: 978-1-63158-494-7



Printed in China





Disclaimer



Neither the author nor the publisher can be held responsible for any loss or claim arising out of the use, or misuse, of the suggestions made herein.

HOW TO
FREEZE FOOD



Generally, food should be frozen on the day of purchase (although if it’s stored in the fridge you can extend this time to nearer the useby date). Most ready meals and packaged raw meat and fish come with instructions as to whether they are suitable for freezing. Follow the label recommendations for how long you should store food in the freezer. If you exceed this date, there will be a deterioration in quality and texture.



If you’re buying food from a butcher or deli counter, ask the sales assistant if it is safe to freeze it. Sometimes raw products have been previously frozen, meaning there’s an opportunity for unhealthy bacteria to grow if they are re-frozen.



It’s OK to freeze meat and fish again once they have been cooked in a dish. As a rule, cooked leftover dishes, soups and stews freeze well. Ensure they’re cold before freezing.



Use freezer bags with sealing clips or zip-lock tops and a permanent marker to label each bag. Clip tightly or fill to the top—don’t leave an air gap. Use rigid food containers for soups and liquids.



Foods that don’t freeze well:



• Raw foods with a high moisture content such as salad leaves, cucumber, watermelon or oranges, unless you plan to eat them frozen; they turn to mush when defrosted.



• Creamy foods like yogurt, cream and custard which will separate into curds and whey.



• Starchy foods like pasta and crumble toppings.

HOW TO
MAKE A BOLOGNESE SAUCE



Here is an adaptation of Italy’s most popular pasta sauce. In this recipe ground lamb is suggested instead of the traditional ground beef.



(Serves six. Prep and cooking time: 40 minutes)





1 lb ground lamb



Splash of olive oil



1 large onion, finely chopped



1 large carrot, peeled and finely cubed



1 garlic clove, peeled and crushed



1 large glass of red wine



14 oz can chopped tomatoes



Pinch of herbes de Provence



Dash of Worcestershire sauce



1 tbsp of tomato purée



5-6 medium mushrooms, chopped



1 beef stock cube, dissolved in 1/2 cup of hot water





Heat the olive oil in a thick-bottomed saucepan over a medium heat. Add the onion and carrot and cook gently for 5 minutes, or until the onion is translucent and the carrot softened. Add the garlic and cook for a further minute.



Meanwhile, add the lamb to a hot frying pan and turn it quickly with two wooden spoons or spatulas. Brown until there is no visible raw meat. Drain the fat from the meat into a dish and set aside.



Add the browned lamb to the pan of softened vegetables. Add all the other ingredients and heat until bubbling. Turn down to a simmer and cook with the lid off for 30 minutes, stirring occasionally. If the sauce becomes too thick add a splash of water. Season with salt and pepper to taste.



Ladle onto cooked spaghetti and sprinkle with grated Parmesan.

HOW TO
STEAM VEGETABLES



Not only is steaming vegetables simple to do, but it comes with benefits: more nutrients are retained; soggy, waterlogged greens are a thing of the past; and there is no need for draining.



It’s not necessary to invest in an electric or tiered stove-top steamer; a molded silicone basket or a folding metal one will do the job just as well, save you money and be less bulky to store.



First, place your steamer basket into a saucepan and fill the pan with cold water until it almost reaches up to the floor of the basket. Too much water and you will be boiling the bottom layer of veggies; too little and you risk boiling the water away, burning the vegetables and the pan. Prepare your chosen vegetable and place in the basket. Put the pan lid on, ensuring that it fits tightly to prevent the steam from escaping. Bring the water to the boil, then turn down the heat sufficiently to maintain the steam.



Most packaged vegetables from supermarkets state the number of minutes required for steaming in the cooking instructions. Alternatively, cook until stalks (or the densest part of the veggie) are soft enough for your liking; test softness with the top of a blunt knife. When the vegetables are cooked use a cloth to lift the steamer basket out. Tip the boiling water away, return the basket of veggies to the pan and replace the lid to keep hot until needed.

HOW TO
MAKE MASHED POTATOES



Floury, fluffy potato varieties make particularly excellent mashed potatoes. Although you can mash most potatoes, waxy types make it harder to achieve a good result and fingerling or new potatoes are often too dense for the job.



Discard any potatoes with green patches and dig out any sprouting eyes with the sharp end of a potato peeler. If you’re not following a recipe, allow two to three medium-sized potatoes per person.



Skin on or off? It’s your choice. If you’re cooking a meal to impress then peel your spuds for an even texture and color. Or take the lazy option: leave the skins on and congratulate yourself on getting more nutrients.



METHOD



1 Chop the potatoes into equal-sized chunks and place them in a saucepan with sufficient cold, salted water to cover them. Put the lid on and bring them to the boil, then turn down the heat and simmer for about 15–20 minutes until the potatoes are soft through to their centers. Test this with a blunt knife.



2 Drain well, return them to the pan with a generous pat of butter and a splash of milk. Mash until smooth with a potato masher or fork, adding more butter and milk if necessary. Season generously with salt and pepper and serve.



3 If you are feeling adventurous, add herbs, garlic, cheese, grainy mustard or horseradish to your mash.

HOW TO
CARVE A ROAST



A sharpened carving knife is essential and a long carving fork is useful for steadying joints as you cut. A metal carving dish with prongs to grip the meat will also help to retain heat. Warm plates and serving platters in the oven for a minute or two to avoid dishing up lukewarm meat.



Rolled joints with no bones are the easiest to carve as they require simple vertical slicing along the length of the roll. Remove any string from slices before serving. For rolled pork, it’s easier to remove the whole rack of crackling off the joint and break it into strips rather than attempting to cut straight through both at once.



Carve chicken by slicing vertically through one side of the breast, then cut vertically through the leg to create a drumstick and then at the thigh to give two leg joints. Detach the wing. Repeat on the other side. Slice any stuffing into sections.



Leg of lamb or pork is carved in small slices parallel to the big bone running through the joint.



For shoulder joints, use your finger to find the shoulder bone. Cut down into the meat on one side of the bone. Turn the knife to cut horizontally and remove the chunk of meat in one piece. Repeat on the other side of the bone before turning the joint over and cut the bone from the underneath. Trim off any remaining bits of meat. Carve the large pieces into slices against the grain.

HOW TO
MAKE A STIR-FRY



Everyone loves a stir-fry. Simply throw all the ingredients into a wok and it’s ready in minutes. You’ll need a flat-bottomed wok if you’re cooking with electricity, as the whole base needs contact with the heat source.



Basics for stir-frying from scratch:



• Preparing ingredients takes more time than the cooking.



• Prepare all the raw ingredients and line up everything else you need before you start.



• Arrange the ingredients in the order they need to be added: meat and hard vegetables need to go in before more leafy, watery veggies, as they need a longer cooking time; garlic, ginger and chili flakes can be added and cooked for a few seconds before adding any sauce.



• Chop hard vegetables like carrots into thin slices and cut broccoli stems lengthways.



• Noodles that need rehydrating can be cooked separately in boiling water according to the packet instructions and set aside until required.



• You’ll need to keep stirring the ingredients for even cooking.



• Have bowls at the ready to enjoy your stir-fry as soon as it is cooked.



Once you get the hang of stir-frying, you can experiment with ingredients and there are many prepared components available to buy such as ready-cut vegetables, straight-to-wok noodles, seasoned meat strips and stir-fry sauces.

HOW TO
CHOOSE WINE



• Shop at a wine store where advice is readily available. Helpful, knowledgeable sales staff combined with shelf signs to give guidance are good starting points. Some shops will also let you taste certain wines for free; others encourage you to buy a selection of sample glasses of fine wines for a modest price.



• Supermarkets have some good selections and deals on mixed cases and half-cases, which are a good way to find favorites. Online wine companies and societies can offer a good choice for a regular commitment or modest joining fee.



• Look beyond sexy labels on the front of the bottle. Instead, focus on the words on the back to identify what you might like: dry, crisp, acidic, fruity, sweet, light, well-rounded, full-bodied, oaky and so forth.



• It’s an idea to be wary of wines described as “table wine” as these are cheaper blends. They may be good but there is a risk that they will lack depth of flavor, or that they are unbalanced in composition.



• For complementary wine and food pairings, light wines tend to pair well with lighter foods like chicken and fish, while full-bodied wines go with richer foods such as red meat and strong cheeses. Contrasting flavors can match, too—check bottle labels for pairing guidance. Spicy foods work well with a crisp, acidic, white wine with a medium to low alcohol content.

HOW TO
POP A CHAMPAGNE CORK



Provided the bottle has not fallen over or been shaken up, this technique should ensure that you can crack it open in style without spilling a drop (but have a cloth handy, just in case!).



With your champagne flutes at the ready, unpick a little of the foil around the bottle neck to access the flattened twist of wire which holds the metal cap in place (called the “cage”). Untwist the wire to loosen the cage but don’t remove it from the bottle. Keep your hand over the cork to keep it safe, and be careful to not point it at anyone in the room or at anything valuable.



Grasp the bottle firmly by the base in one hand and hold the cork with the other. Make sure to keep the bottle at a 45-degree angle. Twist the base of the bottle gently keeping hold of the cork as it comes out—you will still experience the satisfying pop as it releases and see the appealing vapor wisps rise into the air. This is the most sophisticated way to open a champagne bottle and keeps you firmly in the driving seat.



Occasionally, the cork can be stubborn. If you come across resistance, alternate the twisting motion with a little upward leverage with your thumb, while keeping hold of the cork, until you achieve the desired result.

HOW TO
SEW ON A BUTTON



Buttons have a habit of unravelling, so make sure to re-attach them before they come off completely and become lost.



1 Thread a needle with thread, either to match the button or other button threads.



2 Knot the end of the thread.



3 Pass the needle from the underside of the fabric through one of the tiny stitch holes from where the button was before.



4 Pull the thread all the way through so the knot is touching the back of the fabric.



5 Push the needle through any hole in the back of the button.



6 Move the button down the thread. Hold it in the correct position on the fabric.



7 Pass the needle through either the adjacent or opposite hole, depending on whether matching buttons have been stitched on diagonally or with parallel lines of stitching. Pull the needle out through to the underside.



8 Repeat the process so that threads pass through each of the button’s holes four to five times.



9 Don’t stitch the button on too tight or it will be hard to use. Wind the thread once around the underside of the button.



10 Fasten off on the underside of the fabric.

HOW TO
FOLD BEDSHEETS



Ideally, when you take flat sheets out of the washing machine you need another pair of hands to help you pull and fold them into shape, particularly if they are super-king size.



You’ll need some room space. Find all four corners and ask your helper to take the top two corners, while you keep hold of the other two. Walk away from each other with arms outstretched until the damp sheet is taunt. Hold on tight to your corners while both of you give the sheet a couple of firm tugs, outwards and away from you both. This action helps to remove a lot of awkward creases and straightens the outer edges making ironing much easier. Walk towards each other, matching your corners. While one person holds all the corners the other can pick up the fold. Repeat the stretching and folding process one more time, then peg out on the line or fold to fit a drying rack.



Ironed bedsheets can be folded into the best square or rectangular shape to fit their storage space.



Fitted sheets are convenient to use, if a little tricky to fold. Place them on a large flat surface with the elasticated side pieces flapped over on top and smooth the material flat. Take one of the short edges to match up with the other one, tucking in any stray side-piece fabric. Repeat this folding action until the sheet is the desired size for storage.

HOW TO
DO YOUR LAUNDRY



Wash at high temperatures (140°F or above) to kill bacteria and keep whites brighter. Run the washing machine monthly on empty at 200°F to maintain performance.



Sort your dirty laundry into piles for separate washes:



• Whites for a hot temperature wash (bedding, towels, underclothes, tea towels, dishcloths, flannels).



• Colored cottons suitable for a hot wash (as above).



• Whites for a warm wash (shirts, T-shirts, skirts, shorts, jeans, trousers).



• Coloreds for a warm/cool wash (as above).



• Delicates for a cool/gentle wash (silk, lace, mesh, synthetic clothing).



• Woolens and silk (sweaters, scarves, gloves). Wash these by hand unless you have a hand-wash/woolens or silk setting on your washing machine.



TOP TIPS



• Colors will run on some clothes if they’re not washed at the correct temperature.



• Wash similar colors together (i.e. light colors or dark colors).



• If clothes are only lightly soiled, select the quick wash function on your washing machine.



• Because of their absorbent nature, towels need less washing detergent than other items.



• Close zips and link up hooks and eyes so they can’t catch on other items.



• Empty the machine as soon as possible after the load has finished to prevent clothes smelling damp.



DRYING CLOTHES WITHOUT A TUMBLE DRYER



If hanging clothes outside is not practical, a heated drying rack is a good investment. Pin pants, jeans and skirts at the waistband; shirts, tops and T-shirts should be hung from the shoulders or dried on hangers. Don’t overlap clothing as items will take longer to dry. Dry woolens flat to keep their shape.

HOW TO
VACUUM A ROOM



Ideally, carpets, rugs and other floor areas need cleaning once a week to stop dirt from building up, help to prevent allergy flare-ups and control clothing moths. Always dust a room before you clean the floor, as particles will inevitably drop downwards in the process.



Use the right tools for the job: hand-held vacuums are fine for small areas but you’ll need something bigger to tackle a whole room. There are many lightweight, high-powered vacuum cleaners on sale as well as bagless, cylinder-style models.



Vacuum the room systematically, moving small items of furniture out of the way beforehand.



Make sure that you shift beds and large items of furniture away from the wall periodically to suck up the dust underneath.



Make good use of the attachments to lift dust and dirt from upholstery, awkward spaces and the gap between the floor’s surface and the baseboard.



Vacuum in all directions, letting the vacuum head linger long enough in one place to shift dirt effectively. Most vacuum cleaner heads have different height settings for cleaning different surfaces. Cleaning on the right setting can make a huge difference to the end result.



Change your vacuum bag or empty your cylinder before they fill up or the vacuum cleaner will lose much of its efficiency. For the same reason, never re-use vacuum bags.

HOW TO
CLEAN A TOILET



Don’t just flush and run when you’ve been. Check the toilet to be sure it’s in a pleasant condition for the next person. Take the long-handled toilet brush, usually found in its holder beside the toilet, and scrub away any stubborn residue or streaks left after flushing. Tap the arm of the brush against the side of the seat to shake off drips before transferring back to its holder. It’s considered good manners to leave the toilet seat down—and the lid, too—particularly after a longer visit!



Toilets should be deep cleaned once a week to keep germs and viruses at bay, or more often if there’s been a virulent stomach bug in your household. Wear rubber gloves, kept for this purpose, if preferred.



Carefully squirt strong, thick bleach under the inside rim and round the toilet bowl, or use a special-purpose toilet cleaner for the job.



Leave this on for around 10 minutes to neutralize bacteria while you work on the outside of the toilet (including the flush handle and the area around the seat hinges). Work from the top down to the floor with toilet cleaner and a disposable cloth. Then clean all the seat surfaces, including the lid and the rim under the seat.



With the toilet brush, scrub away at any stains or limescale marks under the rim and inside the toilet bowl. Tip waste water from the toilet brush holder down the toilet. Add a little bleach to the bottom of the holder. Then shut the toilet lid and flush away the bleach.



It’s a good idea to wash the sink and bathroom door handles at the same time.

HOW TO
PAINT A ROOM



Decide on your color once you’ve experimented with samples. Cover a large area of the walls with two coats of the sample color and wait for them to dry before you make your final decision. Remember, the color will look different on a wall in direct light.



Choose the type of paint finish to suit the room: satin and gloss paints are cleanable and therefore good for kitchens and bathrooms; eggshell is popular for walls in rooms with less wear and tear. Make sure you buy enough paint for the job—dark colors and patterned paper can take three coats to cover. Bare plaster will also need a coat of primer.



Stir paint before starting so the color is evenly mixed. If you’re using a roller, cover your paint tray in foil or tight-wrapped cling film before adding paint to make the clean-up op a cinch. Tip enough paint to fill the well of a paint tray a third full. Load the roller with paint by dipping in the tray and rolling it on the flat part of the tray to remove excess paint. Don’t over-saturate the roller or the paint will run and drip.



Always start with the ceiling. Use a paint brush on corners, edges and round light fittings first before using a hand-held paint roller for bigger areas. Use an extension pole on the roller to reach up high. When painting walls work systematically, with a “W” action, blending the paint evenly.



Remove all the masking tape when the paint is dry and leave the windows open to disperse the fumes. Clean brushes and roller equipment in cold water if the paint is water-based. For oil-based paint, soak items in turpentine.

HOW TO
UNBLOCK A DRAIN



Prevention is better than cure! Stop blockages before they happen by adhering to a few basic rules: never put fats or anything other than liquid waste down the kitchen sink and keep long hair from clogging the drains of showers, baths and sinks.



A plunger will remove blockages that occur within the first couple of feet of pipe below a drain. Place the plunger’s mouth over the drain, grasp the handle and plunge up and down until the suction releases the debris causing the problem.



Rather than using a caustic cleaner for regular maintenance, pour a drinking cup of baking soda down the drain, followed by half a cup of vinegar. Leave this to fizz for 30 minutes before flushing it down with around two liters (about four pints) of hot water. Repeat as necessary.



For outside drain blockages that don’t respond to the baking powder and vinegar remedy, you could try a few tablespoons of caustic soda (lye). Put this down the drain then add some water to make it fizz and see if the debris rises to the top. Remove the waste matter using rubber gloves.



If this doesn’t work, you may need to borrow or buy a set of drain rods, which screw together clockwise. Wearing protective gloves, poke the rods into the chamber of the drain and slowly rotate them as you push them in. Remember to rotate them clockwise so they don’t unscrew. After you’ve found the blockage and broken it up with the rods, flush the drain with water.

HOW TO
FIX COMMON BIKE PROBLEMS



RECURRING FLAT TIRES



Check the PSI recommended on the side of your tire to see if your tire pressure is too low. Otherwise, check for debris that might be present inside the tire, or whether the tube has been caught between the rim and the tire.



GRINDING CHAIN



A lack of lubricant will make the chain grate, which can be recognized by a grinding sound. Check the lubrication of your chain every few weeks. Alternatively, your chain may be worn or your derailleurs may need adjustment. Likewise, excess lubrication can cause the chain to skip and attracts dirt to the chain and cassette (the rear gears). Clean them both with a degreaser (available from bike stores) and a small brush, rinse and dry. Add one drop of lubricant to each roller while turning the cranks backwards two or three times. Wipe off any excess on the outer side of the chain as you continue to spin it.



WHEEL OUT OF ALIGNMENT



Readjusting a wheel that’s been knocked out of alignment (out of “true”) takes practice, so if you are not confident it’s best to take your bike into trusted shop to fix this problem.



CHAIN KEEPS COMING OFF



The chain can come adrift if you pedal hard while changing gear. However, should this still happen when you pedal softly, seek professional help from a bike shop. They will need to adjust the front derailleur, which moves the chain from one chainring to the next—a small alteration can damage the works if you’re not skilled at this.

HOW TO
PURIFY WATER



There are many ways to make water safe to drink. Here are some of them.



BOILING



This is a reliable method but may not always be the most convenient. Bring the water to the boil over a campfire or stove, in a pan or heatproof container, and keep it at a rolling boil for 10 minutes.



WATER FILTERS



Drip filters have a pouch, rather like a medical IV drip, and use gravity to drip the water through a filter. The water can then be sucked through a plastic hose. Survival straws are a robust form of drinking straw attached to a lightweight water filter to let you drink as you go. Pump-action filters push water from one tank, through a filter cartridge, into the clean water tank on demand. These can come with large capacity tanks for group camping.



DISINFECTING TABLETS



Tablets are either iodine- or chlorine-based. Depending on the type, they can take from around 35 minutes to 4 hours to purify water. Iodine tablets work faster but they are not recommended for pregnant women or people with thyroid problems. All tablets tend to leave a disinfectant after-taste, particularly the iodine ones, but it’s possible to remove this effect with neutralizing tablets.

HOW TO
HELP SOMEONE WHO’S HAVING AN EPILEPTIC FIT



A seizure happens when there is electrical activity in the brain; there are many different kinds. This is what to do if someone is having a convulsive (tonic-clonic or clonic) seizure:



• Don’t move them unless they are in a dangerous place, but do move furniture and other objects away from them.



• Note the start and finish time of the seizure.



• If they haven’t collapsed but appear confused or unaware, comfort them and make sure that they are not able to hurt themselves.



• Talk to them calmly and quietly.



• Support their head with something soft if they are on the ground.



• Loosen any restrictive clothing round their neck to help their breathing.



• Don’t put anything in their mouth, including your fingers.



• When convulsions have ceased, turn them so they are lying on their side and stay with them until they’ve recovered.



The CDC advises you should dial 911 if it’s the first time someone has had a seizure; the seizure lasts for more than five minutes; or if the person doesn’t regain full consciousness, or has a series of seizures without regaining consciousness.

HOW TO
CHECK FOR ABNORMAL MOLES



Pick a room with good lighting and remove all your clothes. Start at your head and work your way down your body. Check all areas of skin thoroughly, including your scalp, behind your ears, around your nose, between your fingers and toes and—not forgetting the great divide—your bottom! Ask a trusted friend to help you check areas that you can’t see, or use a mirror.



The “ABCDE” of moles, used by dermatologists and other health bodies, classifies types to look out for:



• Asymmetrical: Normal moles are round and grow evenly. Melanomas expand at an uneven rate and are therefore asymmetrical.



• Borders: Unhealthy moles are prone to have ragged or blurred borders. Standard moles are rounder with clearly defined borders.



• Color change: A normal mole is the same color throughout. A melanoma can vary in color. If a mole becomes darker in color this is a sign that it is possibly cancerous.



• Diameter: Problem moles are usually larger than 0.25 inches but this is not a definite sign. Sizes of cancerous and normal moles can vary. Look for any changes in size.



• Elevation or enlargement: Moles that become raised, inflamed or swollen need to be professionally checked, as well as those that start to bleed, crust or itch.



Check any suspicious mole with your doctor, who can refer you to a dermatologist if they think specialist treatment is required.

HOW TO
APPLY FOR A JOB/WRITE A COVER LETTER



While many jobs these days involve online applications, it is still a common requirement to send your resume and a cover letter or email.



For the letter, follow the rules for formal letter writing and always quote the job reference in the header to clarify which job you are applying for. The letter needn’t be long and mustn’t exceed a single sheet of paper, so don’t ramble. It needs to supplement your resume by focusing on why you want the job principally, as well as your suitability and enthusiasm for the role. Find a way to reference a positive fact about the company so it shows you’re up-to-date about what it does and where it is heading.



If you’re not confident about spelling or grammar, ask a family member or friend to read the letter before you send it off. If you are applying online or by email, save your letter as a PDF as any computer can view this file format.



If you are writing on spec to see if a company you’d like to work for has a vacancy, do your research on the organization. Look up who you should address the letter to and address them by name, if possible. This will help your letter stand out!



It’s rare to be asked to apply in writing. Should this be the case, write neatly and legibly using a good pen and simple writing paper. Choose an envelope big enough to accommodate your resume without overfolding it.

HOW TO
ACE AN INTERVIEW



Whether you’re doing your interview online or face-to-face, treat it seriously and do your research beforehand. Practice delivering some answers before the interview. Be clear on why the organization needs you and how you can add value.



If you are being interviewed online, set up your device with a plain background behind you and in a quiet room where there will be no interruptions. Position the camera so you can be seen from the waist up. Test all aspects of your tech before the interview. Make eye contact with the camera, sit up straight and don’t talk too fast.



Dress in the style appropriate for the company or organisation you hope to join. If you’re doing a face-to-face interview, arrive early and don’t be spotted checking out your phone screen while you’re waiting to be called in. Ensure it’s switched off before you arrive.



Group interviews are often conducted to see how you might work with others as a team. Make sure you listen to what’s going on and that you are seen to say something. Dilemmas may be posed to test how you might handle a client or customer query; your approach to the issue might be more important than knowing the “right” solution.



Try to appear relaxed in a one-to-one interview, without coming across as nonchalant. Aim to make at least 50 percent of the contribution to the dialogue. Sell yourself and your talents well but know when to stop.

HOW TO
UNDERSTAND EMAIL ETIQUETTE



• Clarify the topic concisely in the subject line and update it if the discussion changes.



• Never put anything in an email that you wouldn’t say in public.



• Use good English—no slang, text abbreviations, emojis or inappropriate exclamation marks. Re-read your email before you send it. Check for typos or missing attachments.



• Stay formal until you know your recipient better. “Dear” can become “Hello” or “Hi” over time. Likewise, stick with “Kind regards” or “Regards”—”Best wishes” comes later.



• Have a proper email signature set-up which includes your name, title and full contact details.



• Respond to all points raised by the sender. Be clear on what the next actions should be.



• Thank recipients if they’ve done something helpful; thank them in advance for something you’re asking them to do.



• Send large or numerous attachments via a file transfer system and notify the recipient.



• Don’t fire off a reply when you are angry. Wait until your emotions are under control.



• Protect people’s privacy when emailing groups by hiding their email addresses in a “bcc” box.



• Pick up the phone, make a Skype call or FaceTime. Sometimes issues need discussion that’s better handled by a conversation. Follow up with an email once an action has been agreed.

HOW TO
MANAGE YOUR TIME



Procrastination is your enemy! Vow to start early in the day to achieve more and crack on.



Make a “To do” list of tasks to be accomplished. Date your list and refresh it periodically; write it by hand if you’re motivated by seeing how many items you have completed. Put a dash against items that can’t be finished until others have been responded to, to show yourself some progress, and break down big tasks with sub-entries to tick off as you work through them.



Each day, tackle the two or three most important tasks first. Focus on these crucial jobs without distraction and tick them off your list. You’ll have done what’s essential and feel good that your load has been lightened.



Set yourself a target time limit for completing tasks—for instance, doing a set amount of work before lunch. Be realistic about how long it will take you to do a task and don’t beat yourself up if it was more complex than it first appeared. Don’t let unimportant details in the task ambush your time. The key to completion is to not let unnecessary distractions eat away at your time, so keep cell phones out of sight and unrelated browser windows shut until you’re done.



Keeping a separate “To do” list for personal things that need to be done or remembered, or that you would like to do, can also help with time management in your private life.

HOW TO
MAKE A GOOD IMPRESSION AT A FORMAL DINNER OR EVENT



Observe the dress code specified on the invitation. Clean, shiny shoes, a crisp shirt and tie and a well-pressed suit show a man who cares about his appearance; for women at a smart wedding it is conventional not to wear black or white, show too much bare skin during the church service or to outshine the bride.



Unless previously agreed with your host, arrive at the time specified on the invitation. This is particularly important for a sit-down dinner or a church service.



At the dinner table, stand until bidden to sit. Once in your seat, unfold your table napkin and place it on your lap. Always wait for your hostess to start eating before you do. This is also helpful if you are unsure about how to eat something unfamiliar, or what cutlery to use and when.



Talk to the person on your left during the first course, then to the person on your right during the main course. This way, no one is left out of a conversation.



If the waiting staff are not in constant attendance, ensure that you offer wine, water, condiments and any other item your neighbor might be short of, or that is out of reach, before you serve yourself. Hold serving dishes for them while they help themselves.



Don’t overindulge!

HOW TO
GIVE A TOAST



Although the host traditionally proposes the first toast on most formal occasions, when friends gather informally, as a guest you can toast your host to thank them for their hospitality and any other reason you wish—friendship, long life, love, congratulations, good fortune or happiness.



Toasts should not be confused with speeches; they should be kept short and to the point.



Before leading the toast at a semi-formal occasion, check that the guests’ glasses and your own have been charged before commencing. Attract everyone’s attention by standing, or sitting yourself in a prominent place.



Briefly introduce yourself and the reason for the gathering. Go on to express a goodwill wish towards the future of the person(s) concerned—for example, “May you be ever light of heart and calm of mind.” Ask the assembly to raise their glasses by raising your own glass while saying, “To [name of person/subject of toast].” They should respond by repeating your toast. Take a sip from your glass which will allow them to follow your example.



If all around you are seated, ask them to, “Please stand and raise your glasses to…” Official toastmasters at formal events will use more flowery language: “Lords, ladies and gentlemen, please be upstanding for…” Note that at a wedding reception, etiquette dictates that it’s the best man’s job to propose the first toast.

HOW TO
MAKE SMALL TALK



Arrive early to parties and functions. Why? Because it is easier to find another person on their own in the early stages of a gathering and being one of the first few lessens the chance of everyone already talking in groups when you turn up. However, if you’ve had to come later, target a small group to join that’s left a gap in its circle.



Although deep down we are conditioned to think that small talk is trivial, we need to use it to connect with others. Small talk is the basis on which more authentic conversations grow.



When you walk into an event, you might be apprehensive. You won’t be alone in this. By reaching out to converse with others you can put both them and yourself at ease.



An observation about anything in the room can be all that is needed as an ice-breaker. For example, “Wow! These flower arrangements are lavish!” You haven’t given away what you think about the flowers or criticized the host’s choice of flora; you’ve shown yourself to be friendly and open. You could follow it up with, “I wish I knew more about flowers. Do you know what those big ones in the center are?” Allowing the other person to display their knowledge is a good starter and even if they know as little about flowers as you, you have discovered common ground.



Asking questions is another way to start a conversation. The wedding classic is, “Do you know the bride or the groom?” Other openers are, “How do you know our hosts?” or “Where are you from?” Listen to the answers for clues about where to go next with the conversation and bring out your inner journalist! When the other person names their hometown, ask them what it’s like to live there or what led them to be there. Asking their opinion is another technique—for example, “What did you think of that course module?” When you are asked about yourself resist monosyllabic answers, which are conversation killers. Offer conversation bait instead. If the other person asks, “What have you been up to today?”, instead of responding with “Nothing exciting” say something like, “I’ve been busy packing up my apartment”—this can give them a steer on what to ask you next.



Keep off contentious subjects like politics and religion. Learn at least one new fact a day from a reliable source and you’ll be amazed at how often these can be used as conversation topics. Broadening your knowledge of the world pays off on these occasions.



Striking up conversations with strangers takes practice. Don’t be put off by the odd disaster. You’ll become adept at it before you know it!

HOW TO
ASK FOR HELP



There is no weakness in asking for help. On the contrary, the weakness is in thinking you know the answer to everything.



We all need help to thrive, accomplish and develop. This often includes asking for help from others to fill in gaps in our own knowledge or understanding, or for advice in solving a dilemma. Other people can often point us in the right direction, even if they can’t provide a direct answer.



You might be surprised to find that people often want to help you, as it makes them feel good and useful. Phrase your request in a flattering way to unlock this instinct. You might say, “I’m a bit stuck and I know you’re just the right person to help me with this” or “Please may I ask for your advice?” There may be occasions when you are physically ill and need help. Your friends and family will undoubtedly ask if you need help, but to turn the kind offers into actual action requires you to be specific about what sort of help you need—for example, buying and preparing food, picking up medication, changing bed linen or providing transportation. Ask your willing helpers to take on an errand. Match the task to the person’s strengths and your comfort level if the task is an intimate one. Resist micromanaging how it’s done and always thank your helpers, no matter how small their contribution.

HOW TO
GIVE A COMPLIMENT



Complimenting others should figure in your armory of social skills. It’s an excellent way to show appreciation and give praise where it is due.



TOP TIPS



• Remember to do it, but be mindful not to overdo it or be too fulsome in your offer of praise—you don’t want to make the other person uncomfortable.



• Charm others with compliments but always be genuine and sincere.



• Compliment people on specifics about their personal taste and skills, such as their clothing, interior decorating, cooking or singing. Saying something rewarding about another’s personality trait will be regarded as special but you need to know the person well for this.



• Be mindful of paying compliments to someone you are making a sales pitch to—you are more likely to put them on their guard.



• Never underestimate how motivating praise can be, in or out of the workplace. A compliment paid on a small thing well-done can be just as important as acclaim for a big project—sometimes it’s more important. Encouragement at just the right moment can boost a flagging morale or buy you willingness from someone else to go the extra mile when you need a favor.



• If you hear good things about a person when they’re not present from a third party, do pass it on and watch them smile.



• Finally, remember: a backhanded compliment isn’t a compliment; it’s a snide remark.

HOW TO
RESPOND TO CRITICISM



It’s instinctive to default to a defensive mode when we’re criticized. We can become angry, dismissive of the criticism, make an excuse or respond with a complaint about the other person.



There is value in constructive criticism, as it can help us grow or give us greater self-awareness in our dealings with friends and family. Taking what’s said into account can improve your interpersonal skills and your relationships.



You may want to counter negative, or seemingly unfair, criticism with a perspective of your own. Whether criticism is positive or otherwise, here’s how to deal with it graciously:



• Process what you’ve been told before you react. This gives you a moment to control those impulsive emotions.



• Acknowledge what has been said by paraphrasing it back. For instance, say, “So I think you are saying that…” This keeps the conversation open.



• Ask for further feedback and listen closely to what is being said without interruption. If you agree with the other person, respond by saying so and stating the action you will take to rectify the point made, then thank them for pointing out the issue.



Ask questions if you don’t fully understand what is being criticized and try to pin down what that person feels can be improved in future.



Rational conversation is the best remedy for unfair criticism. Stay calm. Sometimes others might need to see things from your point of view to realize they’ve made a misjudgement.

HOW TO
MAKE FRIENDS



Relocating to a new city can prise you away from your home-based friends. If you are a new undergraduate, there are many opportunities to meet fellow students during Orientation Week, through joining societies, participating in sport or on your course. Taking a new job in a strange place means those ready-made chances of friendship are not available. You’ll need to work harder to reach potential friends and it can take a while to build a new circle of people.



TOP TIPS



• Accept invitations from your new work colleagues, unless it’s completely out of your comfort zone. They and their wider friendship group might help you to meet new companions.



• Joining a club or group, or participating in local community activities, can provide other routes to potential friendships.



• Be bold enough to strike up a conversation. Be likeable by being interested in that person. If you get on well and would like to see them again, suggest that you exchange contact details. There may be a common activity you’ve discovered in conversation that you can do together.



• Organize a gathering and suggest your new acquaintances bring another friend along.



• Remember that patience is often required. While instant connections can turn into lifelong friendships, with some people you have to let it bubble along, getting to know them by degrees until they are ready to deepen the acquaintance.

HOW TO
BE A GOOD LISTENER



• Pay attention. That includes making eye contact, not interrupting the other person and concentrating on them without being distracted by other people or things.



• Give the other person space to explain how they feel or what is troubling them without prejudice. Be tolerant of what is being said in order to be supportive, even if it’s not in line with your own opinions.



• Being empathetic doesn’t mean hijacking the conversation with examples of what has happened to you, particularly if they are not on the same scale. This will come across as insensitive.



• Be sympathetic. Try not to say, “I know how you feel”, as it’s unlikely that you do and it will sound offensive and false. Better to say, “It must be difficult to deal with your feelings about this.” Don’t jump in with judgements. Your ears are needed more than your views.



• Hold back on offering a solution too soon into the conversation, it can sometimes come across as a bit dismissive. Wait until you are asked for one, or it’s obvious it’s wanted. Sometimes to share a problem or articulate thoughts out loud is enough for the speaker.



• Respect the speaker’s trust in you by considering what has been shared as confidential.



• Following up the subject later shows you care about the speaker, unless instinct tells you that it is something they would prefer not to be brought up again.

HOW TO
LODGE A COMPLAINT



Contact the business that you have a grievance against as soon as possible by phone, email or letter. Address your complaint to the head of the department if you can.



In the case of a purchase from a seller or an issue with a service provider, check their terms and conditions first to understand your rights. Set out your complaint in the body of an email or letter and include copies of relevant receipts, invoices and contracts. Quote any reference numbers in your correspondence. Keep a copy of your complaint and all the documents you include with it.



If you can’t resolve the issue satisfactorily with the company concerned you may be able to take it to an Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR). Companies operating in certain sectors are obliged to offer this service. Other industry sectors such as builders and vacation companies might be signed up to their relevant trade association. These types of bodies can offer independent mediation and arbitration to help settle the issue. Arbitration outcomes are final and you can’t take your complaint further if you don’t like the outcome.



Contacting an ombudsman is an option when you can’t agree with a company over service or administrative errors.



Taking a company to the small claims court for amounts of up to about $5,000 is the ultimate action you can employ, but you will need to prove that you have tried other ways to seek reparation. The claim ceiling in other states and countries may vary.

HOW TO
REMEMBER NAMES



Ever been introduced to someone who doesn’t look like their name? You’ve been told she’s called Anna and your focus is lost as you decide they look like more like a Sandy. Suddenly, you can’t remember what they’re really called because you’ve lost concentration.



Train your brain to cope with remembering names as it makes people feel valued—plus it’s rude if you come out with the wrong name and makes you appear rather foolish.



Start by making sure that you listen; if you’re busy thinking of what you are going to say next, you’re not listening.



Resolve to concentrate hard to hear a name when you are next introduced to someone and repeat their name back to them as you greet them while you look them in the eye. Commit the name to memory. Build up your technique so you can cope with trickier group introductions.



Find a way that works for you to retain the name. This can be by referencing the person’s name in the subsequent conversation, or finding a visual or linguistic association. For example, picture in your head another Anna you know—a friend, relative or celebrity. Try a mnemonic for complicated names, so Kim Kardashian might become “Kim dashes to the car with Ian”. Maybe you can remember a physical feature better to make the connection, or fix upon an item of clothing.



After a party or a business event, try to review who you have met and recall their names again.

HOW TO
NETWORK



It’s important to identify what your objective is before you start to network. This will make you more effective. Perhaps you want to further your career, create sales opportunities, make more friends or take a hobby to new level.



Networking requires patience; when you feel you’re not getting anywhere, this is often when you strike gold with a contact who is a door-opener to a new opportunity.



Much networking can be done online via social media platforms and forums, such as LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter and Instagram. Set your profile description as bait for those you might want to attract and research the hashtags that will reach out to them, or to find the influencers you seek. Send personalized messages explaining why you want to network with them. Be thick-skinned if not everyone responds to your requests to connect.



Never underestimate the power of face-to-face networking. Think about which national or local networks, clubs or societies you might join and what they have to offer. Attend events they hold; arrive early to talk to others attending before the main item begins, stay around afterwards to maximize opportunities to meet new contacts or talk to speakers and organizers. Be brave and bold about this; after all, what do you have to lose?



Don’t forget to come with business cards, with your contact details and memorable message or strapline included—something that will stand out about what you do long after your initial meeting.

HOW TO
GET BY IN A FOREIGN COUNTRY



Those of us who aren’t natural linguists do better with a phrase book. Good travel guides often have sections covering how to greet people, how to say “please” and “thank you” and how to ask about transport, tourist information, accommodation and emergency facilities. Lists of local dishes and regional specialities are helpful, too—even if English language menus are available, not all translations are intelligible.



Alternatively, Google Translate’s app will give you phrases and word meanings in over 100 languages, but be aware that there’s no guidance on pronunciation.



Language classes or home-based language learning are worth considering if you intend to spend a lot of time in one country, or plan to make frequent visits.



Do ask local people for help when traveling. Most are happy to assist and a lot can be achieved with a few words and some judicial pointing.



It’s a good idea to look up key etiquette points for the countries you are traveling to. This will safeguard you from causing offence unwittingly. Understand tipping policies and clothing etiquette—such as the requirement to remove your shoes before entering a mosque, to only wear shorts in Vietnam while on the beach, and so forth.



Going beyond the bounds of manners can land you in serious trouble with the authorities; for example, photographing airports, or military and government buildings.



There are additional etiquette rules when doing business internationally that can be deal-breakers if not observed, so make sure you’re aware of these before you go.